

Research

I'm interested in identifying and describing inequalities in social systems such as in health, education and careers, and informing policy decisions that address those inequalities. My PhD research is broadly focused on quantifying barriers to and retention within the scientific and technical workforce for historically excluded populations. I enjoy using a diverse range of data science and social science methods to conduct large-scale, interdisciplinary administrative, survey, network, and text analyses, which often reveal patterns not visible at a smaller scale. My work is also informed by previous research and industry experience in machine learning, AI for social good, computer vision and natural language processing.

Education

2020 —	Ph.D. in Computer Science, University of Colorado Boulder Advisors: Aaron Clauset & Dan Larremore
2022 —	M.A. in Education Policy, University of Colorado Boulder Advisor: Kevin Welner
2018 — 2019	M.S. in Computer Science, Indiana University Bloomington Advisors: David Crandall & Katie Siek Thesis: Detecting Dyslexia in Handwriting Using Neural Networks
2015 — 2019	B.S. in Computer Science, <i>Minor</i> : Math, Indiana University Bloomington

Employment

Employment	
Summer 2024 (Planned)	Data Science Fellow U.S. Census Bureau, Enhancing Health Data Group (Remote)
June 2019 — Aug. 2020	Research Engineer IBM Research, Artificial Intelligence Hardware Group (San Jose, CA)
Sep. 2017 — June 2019	Research Assistant Indiana University Computer Vision Lab (Bloomington, IN)
Summer 2018	Research Intern IBM Research, Artificial Intelligence Hardware Group (San Jose, CA)
Summer 2017	Research Intern MIT Lincoln Laboratory, Machine Learning Group (Boston, MA)
Aug. 2016 — Sep. 2017	Software Development Team Lead Indiana University Kelley School of Business (Bloomington, IN)
Summer 2016	Research Assistant NSF Research Experience for Undergraduates (Bloomington, IN)

Honors & Awards

2021-2024 **NSF Graduate Research Fellowship**

\$37,000/year and tuition for three years of graduate school in a STEM field.

2019 National Center for Women in Technology Collegiate Award

> \$10,000 award that "recognizes technical contributions to projects that demonstrate a high level of innovation and potential impact."

2019 Provost's Award for Undergraduate Research and Creative Activity

> Mathematics & Natural Sciences winner, one of five categories total. Recognizes "outstanding achievement in research by undergraduates."

2019 Teaching Assistant of the Year Award

Indiana University Computer Science department

2015-2016 Emerging Research Scholar, Center of Excellence for Women & Technology

Publication and Presentation Awards

2024 **Bell Family Endowed Computer Science Scholarship**

"In recognition of outstanding research"

2024 Research Expo Winner, CU Boulder Computer Science department

2023 Publication Recognition Award, CU Boulder Computer Science department

2019 Global Challenges Proposal, Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition

Selected proposal, inaugural Global Challenges workshop (10% accept rate)

2019 Best Poster Award, International Conference on Machine Learning

Grants

2022 "Quantifying the origins and impacts of book bans in U.S. schools"

> PI, with Isabelle Langrock (co-PI), Jack LaViolette (co-PI) and Marcelo S.O. Goncalves (co-PI) Russell Sage Foundation & Social Science Research Council, \$1,500

Travel Funding: Summer Institute in Computational Social Science full travel funding (June 2022); CVPR Global Challenges Workshop full travel funding (June 2019); ICML AI for Social Good Workshop travel scholarship & registration fee waiver (June 2019); NCWIT annual conference full travel funding (May 2019); Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing travel scholarship (Sep. 2016)

Publications

Journal Articles

Gendered devaluation underlies faculty retention [Pre-print]

K. Spoon, J. Mendy, M. Martinez, M. Galesic, D. B. Larremore, A. Clauset, L. A. Rivera. Under Review.

2023 Gender and retention patterns among U.S. faculty [Paper]

> K. Spoon, N. LaBerge, K. H. Wapman, S. Zhang, A. C. Morgan, M. Galesic, B. K. Fosdick, D. B. Larremore, and A. Clauset. Science Advances.

Book bans in political context: Evidence from U.S. public schools [Pre-print] 2023

- I. Langrock*, J. LaViolette*, M. S. O. Goncalves*, K. Spoon*. Under Review.
- *All authors contributed equally and are listed alphabetically
- 2021 Towards software-equivalent accuracy on transformer-based deep neural networks with analog memory devices [Paper]
 - **K. Spoon**, H. Tsai, A. Chen, M.J. Rasch, S. Ambrogio, C. Mackin, A. Fasoli, A. Friz, P. Narayanan, M. Stanisavljevic, and G.W. Burr. Frontiers in Computational Neuroscience.
- Noise-resilient DNN: Tolerating noise in PCM-based AI accelerators via noise-aware training S. Kariyappa, H. Tsai, **K. Spoon**, S. Ambrogio, P. Narayanan, C. Mackin, A. Chen, M. Quereshi, and G.W. Burr. IEEE *Transactions on Electron Devices*.

Conference Papers

- 2021 Mushroom-type phase change memory with projection liner: An array-level demonstration of conductance drift and noise mitigation
 - R. L. Bruce, et al. [including K. Spoon]. IEEE International Reliability Physics Symposium (IRPS).
- 2021 Fully on-chip MAC at 14nm enabled by accurate row-wise programming of PCM-based weights and parallel vector-transport in duration-format
 - P. Narayanan, et al. [including K. Spoon]. Symposium on VLSI Technology.
- Neuromorphic computing with phase change, device reliability, and variability challenges C. Mackin, et al. [including **K. Spoon**]. IEEE International Reliability Physics Symposium (IRPS).
- 2019 Reducing the impact of phase-change memory conductance drift on the Inference of large-scale hardware neural networks
 - S. Ambrogio, M. Gallot, **K. Spoon**, H. Tsai, C. Mackin, M. Wesson, S. Kariyappa, P. Narayanan, C.C. Liu, A. Kumar, A. Chen, and G.W. Burr. 65th IEEE International Electron Devices Meeting (IEDM). Ranked 2nd/98 papers.

Workshop Papers

- 2020 Accelerating deep neural networks with analog memory devices
 - **K. Spoon**, S. Ambrogio, P. Narayanan, H. Tsai, C. Mackin, A. Chen, A. Fasoli, A. Friz, and G.W. Burr. *International Memory Workshop*.
- 2019 Can we (and should we) use AI to detect dyslexia in children's handwriting? [Paper]
 - K. Spoon, D. Crandall, K. Siek, and M. Fillmore. AI for Social Good Workshop, NeurIPS.
- 2019 Towards detecting dyslexia in children's handwriting using neural networks [Paper]
 - **K. Spoon**, D. Crandall, and K. Siek. AI for Social Good Workshop, International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML).

Book Chapters

2022 Accelerating deep neural networks with analog memory devices

K. Spoon, S. Ambrogio, P. Narayanan, H. Tsai, C. Mackin, A. Chen, A. Fasoli, A. Friz and G.W. Burr. In *Machine Learning & Non-Volatile Memories*. Ed. C. Zambelli, Springer.

Talks

Quantifying the origins and impacts of book bans in U.S. schools

International Conference on Computational Social Science, Contributed

July 2023

Explaining gendered retention patterns in academia

(Planned) University of Colorado Boulder Academic Leadership Conference, Invited	Aug 2024
Academic Analytics Research Center, Invited	Feb 2024
University of Colorado Boulder Office of Faculty Affairs, Invited	Dec 2023
Atlanta Conference on Science & Innovation Policy, Contributed	May 2023

Women in Network Science & Diversify NetSci Satellite, Contributed International Conference on Computational Social Science, Contributed International Conference on the Science of Science & Innovation, Contributed	July 2022 July 2022 June 2022
Accelerating deep neural networks	
International Memory Workshop, Invited	May 2020
Towards detecting dyslexia in children's handwriting using neural networks	
American Handwriting Analysis Foundation, Invited	Nov 2019
Computer Vision for Global Challenges Workshop, CVPR, Contributed	June 2019
AI for Social Good Workshop, ICML, Contributed	June 2019
Posters	
Mapping U.S. education pathways to scientific and technical careers	
(Planned) American Educational Research Association Annual Meeting	Apr 2024
Explaining gendered retention patterns in academia	
International Conference on Computational Social Science	July 2023
The elite undergraduate backgrounds of U.S. professors	
International Conference on Computational Social Science	July 2022
International Conference on the Science of Science & Innovation	June 2022
Towards detecting dyslexia in children's handwriting using neural networks	
AI for Social Good Workshop, NeurIPS	Dec 2019
AI for Social Good Workshop, ICML, Best poster award. [Poster]	June 2019

Work in Progress

The earnings gap in academia

Leading a collaboration with the U.S. Census Bureau Center for Economic Studies to link faculty employment records with detailed restricted-use demographic and earnings information over time to study earnings gaps in academia across gender, race, parenthood, and institution.

Mapping U.S. education pathways to scientific and technical careers

As the thesis for my education policy degree, I am leading a data linkage project with restricted-use data from the U.S. Census Bureau and college and careers data from the National Center for Science and Engineering Statistics to measure how access to STEM careers differs for students from different geographic and demographic backgrounds, and for those who took different educational pathways to their jobs.

Teaching

F 2019	Professional Development Teaching Assistant IBM Research Upskilling Class on Deep Learning
F 2018, Sp 2019	Lead Graduate Teaching Assistant CS C343: Introduction to Data Structures & Algorithms

Sp 2018 Undergraduate Teaching Assistant

CS C343: Introduction to Data Structures & Algorithms

F 2016, Sp 2017, F 2017 Undergraduate Teaching Assistant

CS C241: Discrete Mathematics for Computer Science

Undergraduate Research Mentoring

•	Joanna Mendy	CU Sociology & Political Science	2022-2023
•	Maria Martinez	CU Political Science & Ethnic Studies	Summer 2022
•	Swag Das	CU Computer Science	Spring 2022
•	Jordan Roos	CU Biomedical Engineering	Spring 2022

Service

•	CU Computer Science PhD Application Mentor	2020-present
•	You're @ CU Graduate Student Mentor	2022-present
•	McNair Scholars Graduate Student Mentor	2021-2022
•	CU Engineering Mentor for Underrepresented First-Year Undergraduates	2020-2022
•	Lead Ambassador, IU Luddy School of Informatics, Computing & Engineering	2016-2019
•	Software Development Intern, Serve IT Nonprofit Technology Clinic	2016-2017

Reviewing: eLife, Social Policy & Administration, Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies

Other Professional Activities

•	Data Institute, National Center for Education Statistics (NCES).	2024
	Selected participant. Competitive 6-month training program funded by NCES.	
•	Summer Institute in Computational Social Science at Duke University	2022
	Selected participant. Funded by the Russell Sage Foundation.	
•	Grad Cohort for Women Workshop, Computing Research Association (CRA)	2021
	Attendee.	